<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To every individuall member of the supream authority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England. The humble addresse of Lieu. Col. John Lilburn, by way of answer to a most false and scandalous printed petition, delivered at the House door against him, by one William Huntington, upon Wednesday the 26 of November. 1651</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E647_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867764</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88258)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 99:E647[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To every individuall member of the supream authority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England. The humble addresse of Lieu. Col. John Lilburn, by way of answer to a most false and scandalous printed petition, delivered at the House door against him, by one William Huntington, upon Wednesday the 26 of November. 1651</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "25 June 1651. At the committee of Parliament for removing obstructions in the sale of deans and chapters lands." and "The humble petition of William Huntington of Billingham in the County of Durham, Yeoman".</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: John Lilburne. London this 28 Novemb, 1651.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120088:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO EVERY INDIVIDUALL MEMBER of the Supream Authority of the Parliament of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Humble Addreſſe of Lieu Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> by way of Anſwer to a moſt falſe and ſcandalous Printed Petition, delivered at the Houſe door againſt him, by one <hi>William Huntington,</hi> upon Wedneſday the <hi>26</hi> of <hi>November. 1651:</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT by vertue of a particular Act of Parliament bearing date the 30 of <hi>July,</hi> 1650. your ſupplient was inabled to purchaſe as much Dean and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Lands (as part of his reparations for his bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous ſufferings by the Star-Chamber) as did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to One Thouſand five hundred eighty three pounds eighteen ſhillings and four pence, at ten years purchaſe in poſſeſſion, and propotionable in reverſion; by vertue of which Act, he repaired to the Contractors at <hi>Gurney</hi> Houſe, and there amongſt other things found certain Farms in the Mannor of <hi>Billingham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> where his Father and kindred lives unſold, and to the beſt of his remembrance, the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vay was returned eighteen moneths before the date of his ſaid Act, and at that time when he begun to look after the ſaid Farms, hee did not hear of any one man in the world that was about the buying of them; but finding them abſolutely free, in a Towne that to the beſt of his knowledge he before that time never ſee in his life, nor knew not, nor ever ſaw with his eyes to his knowledge any one of the faces of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiers thereof; nor before his purchaſe never had any treaty by letter,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120088:2"/>word of mouth, or meſſage, with any one of Them, ſaving That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Time of his purchaſe, one M. <hi>Richard Marſhall</hi> came to him in the name of M. <hi>Gaſcoign Eden,</hi> (who had certain yeares remaining in one of the ſaid Farms) and for him deſired to deal with your ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the faid Farm; unto which he very well remembers he replied to the ſaid M. <hi>Marſhal</hi> in theſe words, or to this effect; That M. <hi>Eden,</hi> nor none elſe could not bee juſtly offended at him for buying the ſaid Farms, foraſmuch as he did not goe about to buy any of their Tenant rights, or to meddle with any thing belonging to them, for about a year and a half after their preemption was expired; and the Market was as free for him as for any man in <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially conſidering That no man in the world, That he could hear of, was endeavoring to buy any of the ſaid Farms, when he began his purchaſe; and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket on his part being ſo free as it was, he was reſolved to ſell none of them, having already ingaged to ſome eminent friends of his, men of honour, That were inſtrumental in getting the ſaid Act to paſs, That he would keep Them as his Inheritance for him and his heirs; and having perfected his Purchaſe, and got his Conveiances ſigned, ſealed, and inrolled, he indeavoured to look after the rents and profits of the ſaid Farms, which we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Five in number, and a certain Rent Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Haver</hi> Malts, which were to bee paid by the Occupiers of 16 Farms in the ſaid Town of <hi>Billingham,</hi> and finding the ſaid Tenants or Occupiers of the ſaid Farms did deny the States Title, and would not pay their rents, he, in or about the 15 of <hi>Janu.</hi> 1650. complained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by Petition to the Honourable Committee of Parliament, <hi>for remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Obſtructions,</hi> who thereupon ordered the ſaid Tenants to pay their rents, or elſe within Twenty days after notice of the ſaid Order, to appear in the inner Court of Wards, To ſhew cauſ to the contrary, as appears by the Original of the ſaid Order, recorded in Mr. <hi>Nowels</hi> Book, Clerk to the ſaid Committee; unto which, for more certainty, he referreth himſelf. Upon the ſerving of which ſaid Order, all the ſaid Tenants yeilded conformity and obedience in paying the ſaid Rents, ſaving the Complainant <hi>Will. Huntington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto whom at <hi>Billingham,</hi> in or about <hi>Feb.</hi> 1650. your Supplient repaired, and in the preſence of his Father Mr. <hi>Richard Lilburn,</hi> and his Couſen <hi>George Blacket,</hi> and the Father of the ſaid <hi>Huntington,</hi> and ſeveral of the neighbours and kinsfolks of the ſaid <hi>Huntington,</hi> proffered the ſaid <hi>Huntington</hi> and his wife, (who was not long before the wife of one <hi>Shippard,</hi> poſſeſſor of the ſaid Farm) that if they pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him for their Landlord, and turn Tenant to him, he having bought the Farm in preſent poſſeſſion, they ſhould have it at the ſame rate he paid for it, and that it was valued in the Survay, which was 18 <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> 7 <hi>d.</hi>
               <hi>per annum;</hi> or if They would not be his Tenants, in the ſecond place, hee proffered Them, That if They would chooſe two neighbours of the Town, hee would chooſe two more to value the Corn They had ſown upon his Ground without his leave or licence. Conditionally They would quietly ſurrender him the poſſeſſion of his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120088:2"/>own, he would give Them in ready money what They valued the ſaid Corn at, and five pound more: And in regard her firſt husband had left her divers ſmall children, in a poor condition, he would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly take one of her boyes, and new clothe him from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot, and take him into his own Family, and bring him up at his own coſts and charges in that which he found him moſt capable of, till he became Twenty years old. Or</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if They would doe neither of theſe, but ſtood upon Their Title, Then he told Them their regular way was to ſtate Their Title in a Petition to the Committee of Parliament, appointed to deſide ſuch things; and if they would doe that, he proffered them that ſeeing they might be deſtitute at <hi>London</hi> of friends, he would preſent their Petition for them, and indeavour to the utmoſt of his intereſt to get Them a ſpeedy Anſwer, and ingage unto Them upon his reputation, That he would not either directly or indirectly improve in the leaſt his Intereſt or Tongue to impead their Title, further then to crave a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſal for their Farm.</p>
            <p>Unto all which, the ſaid <hi>Will. Huntington</hi> replied, <hi>It was none of his, he had nothing to do with it, it was his wives, and the barns of her firſt huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band;</hi> And ſhe replied, <hi>The Farm was her ayne, and her barns, and ſhe wode leues her heart bloud before either the Parliament or your Supplient ſhould have it.</hi> But after abundance of intreaties by your Supplient uſed unto her not to be foooliſh and mad, and ſo undo and deſtroy her ſelf and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but all in vain; he was forced plainly to tell her the Farm was his, and he had honeſtly bought it and paid for it, and had bought it of thoſe that he durſt not preſume otherwiſe but that they had right to ſell it, and would make the bargain good; and with a little expence of money and time could force her whether ſhe would or no, to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up the poſſeſſion of it, and then ſhe might repent too late She did not embrace ſome of the foreſaid fair proffers, and ſo he left her as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate at the latter end, as ſhe was at the beginning of the Diſcourſe; and coming up immediatly to <hi>London,</hi> he wrote down to his Father and his ſaid Couſen <hi>Blacket,</hi> to go to her and her husband again before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint was made of Them, and perſwade Them to imbrace ſome of the ſaid Propoſitions, who did ſo accordingly, but all in vain. Upon the knowledge of which, your Suppliant did upon the 22 of <hi>April,</hi> 1651. by a ſecond Petition complain of the ſaid <hi>Will. Huntington,</hi> that he would yeild no obedience to Their ſaid Order, either in paying his rent, or appearing before Them to ſhew cauſe wherefore hee would not. Upon which complaint, the ſaid Committee of Obſtructions, did further Order, That the ſaid <hi>Will. Huntington</hi> ſhould upon ſite or notice of That Order, and Demand made by your Suppliant, or by ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, as he then had, or ſhould appoint to receive the ſaid rent, with the arrearages thereof, as alſo the poſſeſſion of the ſaid Farm pay the ſaid rent for, and give up the poſſeſſion of the Farm aforeſaid, accordingly; or otherwiſe make his perſonal appearance before the ſaid Committee within Twenty days after ſuch ſite or notice of that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120088:3"/>Order; which Order being ſerved by my Agent or Atturney <hi>George Blacket,</hi> and who made abundance of Journeys from his own Houſe thither (which is about Twelve miles off <hi>Billingham</hi>) to perſwade Them without the utmoſt of compulſion to obey the Authority of Parliament, which was all in vain; and for his pains therein <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s people with great gads or cudgels, ſet upon him; and as he hath told me, might have hazarded the knocking him upon the head, had he not well acquitted himſelf with his Sword. After the knowledge of which, before I would goe about to execute the utmoſt extremity, I on purpoſe ſent down my wives brother Cornet <hi>Thomas Duel,</hi> to ſee what he could do with them about yeilding obedience to the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: but fully underſtanding of their perverſe obſtinacy, I ordered the reſerving of the Order in the preſence of one that I hired to come to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to make Affidavit of the ſerving it; which being made, the ſaid Committee made an Order to the Sheriffe by force to put me into the poſſeſſion of the ſaid Farm. The Copy of which Order thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>
                           <hi>25 June 1651.</hi> At the Committee of Parliament for removing Obſtructions in the ſale of Deans and Chapters Lands.</head>
                        <p>WHereas complaint hath been made unto the Committee by Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> that he hath purchaſed of the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for ſale of Deans and Chapters Lands, ſeverall Meſſuages, Lands and Tenements, with their Appurtenances, lying and being in <hi>Billing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> that the Tenants of the ſaid Farms re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to pay their rents, and ſome of them denying the Title of the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> this Committee did the 15 of <hi>January</hi> laſt, order that they ſhould pay their rents, or elſe within twenty dayes after notice of that Order, appeare before this Committee, and ſhew cauſe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And whereas the ſaid Lieut. Colonel in a later Petition (read the 22 of <hi>April</hi> laſt) alledged that all the ſaid Tenants ſubmitted to pay the rents, ſaving <hi>William Huntington,</hi> the ſucceſſor of <hi>Thomas Shippard,</hi> in the ſaid Order of 15 of <hi>January</hi> laſt mentioned, who lives upon and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes the profits of a Farm lying in <hi>Billingham</hi> aforeſaid, part of the ſaid purchaſe rated at 18 l. 15. s. 7. <hi>per Annum</hi> in preſent poſſeſsion, and will in no way obey the ſaid former order; whereupon this Committe did the ſaid 22 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> order that the ſaid <hi>William Huntington</hi> ſhould (upon ſight or notice of that Order and demand made by the ſaid Lieut. Coll. or by ſuch perſon or perſons, as he then had or ſhould appoint to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſaid rent, with the Arreages thereof, as alſo the poſſeſsion of the ſaid Farm,) pay the ſaid rent for, and give up poſſeſſion of the Farm aforeſaid accordingly, or otherwiſe make his perſonall appearance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Committee within twenty dayes after ſuch ſight or notice of that order as aforeſaid. And foraſmuch as oath hath been made unto
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120088:3"/>this Committee, that the ſaid <hi>William Huntington</hi> was upon the third of <hi>June</hi> inſtant, perſonally ſerved with the ſaid Order of this Committe of the 22 of <hi>Aprill</hi> aforeſaid, and wheras it is alledged that the ſaid <hi>William Huntington</hi> hath neither paid the rent for, nor given up poſſeſſion of the ſaid Farme, nor appeared before this Committee, according to direction of the ſaid Order of the 22 of <hi>April</hi> aforeſaid: This Committee do ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon order, That (according to an ordinance of Parliament in that caſe made) the Sheriffe of the County of <hi>Durham</hi> aforeſaid, do upon the fight of this Order, repaire unto the ſaid Farm and Farm-houſe, and doe remove the ſaid <hi>William Huntington,</hi> or any for him, or under him out of the poſſeſſion of the ſaid Farm, Farm-houſe, and appurtenances, and doe deliver up the quiet poſſeſſion of the ſaid Farm, Farm-houſe, and all and ſingular the appurtenances thereto belonging, unto the ſaid <hi>Lieut. Col. John Lilburne,</hi> or unto <hi>Richard Lilburne</hi> Eſquire, Cornet <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Dowell,</hi> and <hi>George Blacket,</hi> his Aſſignes or any of them; and if hee finde reſiſtance, to raiſe the <hi>Poſſe Comitatus,</hi> and by force of Arms to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the ſame, and alſo to break open Dores and Gates for the clearing of the poſſeſſion; and the ſaid Sheriffe is authoriſed to commit unto the next common priſon for one moneth, ſuch perſon and perſons as he ſhal find to reſiſt him in the executing of this Warrant.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Jo. Corbet,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Nath. Hallows</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Cor. Holland.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Sallaway.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Trenchard.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Upon the ſerving of which Order upon the Sheriff of the county to <hi>Durham,</hi> he with his men went to <hi>Billingham,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Huntington</hi> and his Wiſe forced them to the utmoſt extremity that could be before they could get the poſſeſsion, which at laſt having obtained, it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up to my Aſſigns named in the foreſaid Order. After which, my occaſions in <hi>Auguſt</hi> leading me down into the North parts on purpoſe to complain againſt Sir <hi>Arthur Heſilrigg</hi> to the <hi>Generall</hi> (he being then an Officer in his Army) for robbing of my Unkle and other of my <hi>Relations</hi> by his Will and pleaſure of their <hi>Colliery at Harraton,</hi> commonly called, <hi>The nine and five Quarter ſeams</hi> of Coles; which the ſaid ſir <hi>Arthur</hi> values in his <hi>Certificate</hi> at 5475 l.<hi>per annum.</hi> I ſay, going into the North, at the Poſt houſe at <hi>York</hi> I met with a large exclamation againſt me for a Tyrant and grand Oppreſſor about the ſaid Farm, being left there by M. <hi>Bowles,</hi> ſometimes a Chaplin in the Army; as the Poſtmaſter told me; which I have cauſe to judge aroſe from ſome of ſir <hi>Arthurs Agents,</hi> one purpoſe to blaſt my Reputation: Unto which I made my defence in the maner that is made before: after which arriving at <hi>Billingham,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Wife came to me for to claim the enjoyment of her crop of Corn. Unto which I anſwered to this effect, I knew none ſhe had, nor had taken none from her; for, if ſhe would ſow a crop of Corn upon my Ground in deſpite of me, and to force me to all the Extremities that in Law I could be put unto to get my own, and by it had legally recoverd it, I knew no other way if ſhe found her ſelf agrieved at me; but to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120088:4"/>take the ſame courſe to right her ſelf againſt me: And in Equity I knew not of a penny ſhe could challenge at my hand; for I did and do believe That a crop of Corn growing upon a Farm let for under 20 pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and upon ſuch ground, as by the Tradition of people there hath bin conſtantly plowed, without ever lying ſwarth for many ſcores of years, if not ſom 100 of years, could countervails a ful years Rent (which then they were almoſt compleat in arrear to me) and thoſe vaſt expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that for almoſt 12 months together I had conſtantly bin at to get poſſeſſion of my own; beſides the loſs of all my time, and divers of my Friends, beſides the charge of reaping, &amp;c. of the ſaid Crop, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo long as ſhe came unto me upon thoſe Terms of claiming it as her own, after ſhe had done what in her lay to blaſt my Reputation, for uſing no other means but what the Law allows me to get my own, after all fair means of Compoſure were ſcorned and rejected by her, and therefore ſhe muſt now doe as ſhe had forced me to do which was to take her couſe at Law. But perceiving that with much art her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches againſt me was much ſpread in the Country; finding at my coming down the Church dores ſhut up, and the Parſon put out of the Living, being a ſat ſequeſtred Living, the profits of which going to I know not what uſe! upon divers firſt days during my abode there, I ſupplyed the ejected Parſons place, with Prayer, and the beſt words of Exhortation and Inſtruction that the Incomes of God upon my Soul inabled me to afford unto the people. And upon a day after the end of our meeting, there being a large Auditory of many hundreds of people, I took occaſion to ſhew what a vain and fruitleſs thing Notions and Speeches are, when the Practiſe or Actions were quire contrary. And hearing of a rumor, That there was hard dealing by me to ſome of my Tenants; which although (as I told them) my own conſcience did not in the leaſt accuſe me, having uſed all the fair means that the wit of man could uſe to avoid extremity of Law, yet ſo willing was I to avoid being my own Judg, That if any one in that Town thought I had done them wrong, let them chooſe one Neighbour, and I would chooſe another, who ſhould hear us both, and to whoſe determination I would bind my ſelf in Bonds to ſtand unto: And I the rather ſpoke it in that place; That ſo my readineſs to give all juſt ſatisfaction to the meaneſt perſons might be taken notice of. After which time, one <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Rutlas</hi> an Inn-keeper in that Town, a fair conditioned man, and her Couſin, ſpoke to me largely about her and her Farm; and after I had made him a Narrative of her evil dealing with me, which he partly knew before, being privy to my firſt proffers to her; I deſired him from me to goe to her and her Husband, and tell them, That if they would under both their hands acknowledg, The Parliament had a right to ſell the ſaid Farm, and that I had a juſt freedom to buy it, I would then (although they had lately been with Sir <hi>Arthur Heſilrig</hi> to petition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.) I would then</p>
            <p>I ſay, lay aſide my right in law to the ſaid crop, and in equity, come to an exact account with them for all that in any kinde of equity
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120088:4"/>they can call theirs, and lay my rent, my disburſments, and charges in getting my poſſeſſion, &amp;c. together, and rather give them more then leſs, it there were any overbalance; but as I told him, ſo long as they continued obſtinate in that opinion, that the Parliament was Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in ſelling their farm, and my ſelf no better then a Rogue in buying it, I would never treat with them, while I lived, and after this one Mr. <hi>Brough,</hi> as I remember his name, being the Miniſter of <hi>Norton,</hi> that joyns to the ſaid <hi>Billingham</hi> came to me about the ſame buſineſs, in her name, unto whom I made the ſame anſwer, in effect as is before expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and told him, that if they would acknowledge the Parliaments title, and that they had a right to ſell it, I would with all my heart, he being Judge, come to an exact equitable account with them, and do that he himſelf ſhould judge to be full of conſcience and honeſty, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I conceived my ſelf not in the leaſt bound unto it by law, but I could never have a return of my deſire from either of them; ſo that in ſome time after, leaving the Country and coming to <hi>London,</hi> I acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally upon Wedneſday laſt, being the 26. of <hi>November</hi> 1651. met with a Petition in print at the Houſe door delivered againſt me; the Copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the ſupreme authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of ENGLAND: <hi>The humble Petition of</hi> William Huntington <hi>of</hi> Billingham <hi>in the Country of</hi> Durham, <hi>Yeoman;</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
                        <p>THat your Petitioner having lately married a poor Widow with four ſmall Children, who had the Poſſeſſion and ancient Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-right of a Farm in <hi>Billingham</hi> aforeſaid, holden by Leaſe of the Dean and Chapter in <hi>Durham,</hi> which with two Cows and a Crop of Corn was the onely maintenance of that whole family, your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner being unable to purchaſe the Reverſion thereof, the Leaſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring, intended to have concluded a Bargain with an Officer of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who propounded to purchaſe the ſaid Tenement, rendring the Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety thereof back to your Petitioner for his Tenant-right, and the ſame had been effected, had not Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Lilborn</hi> interpoſed, concluding the Purchaſe thereof upon the terms of Tenant right, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an Act of Parliament given him in that behalf, together with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Tenements in that Manor, declaring at the time of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, That he neither intended or deſired any of the Tenants Eſtates, had not the Parliament forced him upon that courſe for the gaining of 150 l. which they ought him; further promiſing, that if the Tenants would at any time make good the Rates of his Purchaſe, he would return their Lands and Tenements to them. Now ſo it is, Right Honorable, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilborn</hi> no ſooner perfected his Conveyance, but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately thruſts out your Petitioner, his Wife and four Children, with the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120088:5"/>addition of one to your Petitioner, and moſt barbarouſly and tyrannical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againſt Law and Equity, hath poſſeſſed himſelf of all your Petitioners. Corn upon the ground, and threſhes out the ſame for his own uſe, taking his two Cows from him, with almoſt a years ſtock of Hay, Straw, and a great quantity of Manure, to the value of a Hundred and thirty Pounds, as by the Teſtimony of ſeverall Neighbors here attending at your door it will appear, to the endleſs ruin of your Petitioners whole family.</p>
                        <p>May it therefore move your godly Hearts to pity the ſad and deplorable Condition of your Petitioner, who now ſtands deprived of all his Livelyhood and Subſiſtence, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilborn</hi> leaving him nothing but a poor ſickly Woman and five ſmall children, and not a Cows milk to ſtay their hungry hearts; your Petitioner alſo being much in debt, and likely to lie and rot in Priſon by theſe mercileſs and ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable Practiſes of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilborn,</hi> who is not aſhamed of ſuch unparalleld Cruelties, forcing your Petitioner to travel Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles upon his bare feet, to beg Relief at this Honorable Door being unable to reſiſt his rigid Power, or wager Law with him in his own defence; He therefore humbly beſeecheth your Honors Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilborn</hi> may either return the Moyety of the ſaid Tenement, as was formerly offered to your Petitioner, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe that he may accept the Rate of his Purchaſe according to his own offer, from a Friend of your Petitioner, who is willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue him Tenant at the yearly Rent of the late Survey; and that the illegal taking away of his two Cows and Corn, with divers other Goods upon the ground, may be committed to the Examination of ſuch men as you ſhall appoint, whereby your Petitioner may have ſome Relief in this ſad and diſconſolate Condition he having ſtript him of all his means, leaving him nothing but a ſickly woman and five ſmall Children; which if I may obtain, I ſhall as in duty bound, humbly exhibit my daily Prayers in your behalf, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>NOw moſt noble Senators; having exactly laid down a true Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of the ſtate of this buſineſſe, the Truth of which, I doe ingage hereby to make good by currant proof upon the forfeiture of my reputation for ever, which I value above my life, eſtate, wife, and children, and doe earneſtly deſire at your hands, if it may ſtand with your pleaſure, That Sir <hi>Arthur Heſilrigge</hi> who I do verily believe either by himſelf in perſon, or ſome of his Agents, incouraged the ſaid <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington</hi> or his wife to come to <hi>London,</hi> to complain, and drew the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned falſe and lying Petition for him, which he the rather believes becauſe Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> in the Country told my brother in law M. <hi>Thomas Gore,</hi> as he related to me; That the ſaid <hi>Huntingtons</hi> wife had beene with him, and preferred a Petition againſt me, wherein ſhe complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of ſuch Things, as if he ſhould have done the like, he ſhould have been printed for a Tyrant indeed. I ſay, I deſire, That Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> as for my adverſary, and Col. <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> as for me, and his Excellency the Lord General, as an indifferent perſon, may be fully impowered by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120088:5"/>the Houſe, to hear and examine the Truth of his Narrative in his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of mine in this Addreſſe, and upon a full hearing on both ſides, to puniſh either in body or goods at the pleaſure of them, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny two of them, where They finde the fault to lie in lyes, falſhoods, or any other baſeneſſe, about this particular buſineſſe, which I think is ſo fair, as nothing in the world can be offered of more ingenuity by me, eſpecially in regard I have a viſible eſtate to make him ſatisfaction, and he hath none as he confeſſeth, to make me; he being not in the leaſt made ſo poor by me, but by his own letcherous baſeneſs in converſing with Whores, and getting of Baſtards, which is the open and common brand he lies under in the Town where hee lives; There is but one Thing more in his Petition, I ſhall at preſent touch upon, and that is my taking away Two Cowes from him, ſo That They have not one now to give Them a drop of Milk. Its true, I believe my ſaid Agent <hi>George Blacket</hi> above ſix months ago according to law ſeiſed upon Two poor Cowes of Theirs, for part of my rent, and praiſed them, and proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered either Them or any of Their friends the Cows for the money they were praiſed at; which they refuſing, the Cows hath ever ſince beene kept in a good paſture, and to my knowledg, I do aver it with confidence, hath ſeveral Times ſince I got my poſſeſſion, been freely proffered unto her again both by my ſelf and others, that I have ſent to her for That end, which ſhe hath obſtinately from Time to Time refuſed, although at my being in the Countrey, as I was informed, one of Them was then worth both of Them when they were taken from <hi>Huntington,</hi> they were ſo mended in their fleſh; ſo that if They have never a Cow to give Them Milk, They may thank Their own ſullenneſſe, and not in the leaſt my oppreſſion: And ſo much at preſent to his ſcandalous Petition.</p>
            <p>BUt now moſt Honourable Senators, ſeeing I am compelled for my own preſervation to put pen to paper, vouchſafe me a little liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty farther without offence, and to appeal to you, That if there bee a great man that doth not appear above board, and yet under board, hath a hand in this Petition, who by himſelf or Inſtruments, ſets this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low on, whether is he not run almoſt to death in his reputation, that is forced to flie to ſuch ſlender props as the complaint of This fellow is to ſupport it; ſo pitifully and ſlenderly endeavouring to blaſt the reputation of him that is his purſuer: For</p>
            <p>Firſt, I beſeech you obſerve, That the Complainant and his wife, are a couple that never would in the leaſt yeild obedience to the Orders and Commands of Parliament ſignified by Their immediate Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees; but contemned them, ſcorned Them, and bid open defiance to them, as will appear plainly by the Records of the Committee of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; for which affronting contempts (which is a ſcorning of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) he ought in law, equity, and juſtice, rather be clapt by the heels then to bee heard by you, before hee hath made expiation for his ſaid crimes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I beſeech you obſerve and judge, whether or no before I went to legal extremity, I did not uſe all fair and candid means to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120088:6"/>get mine own, that it was poſſible for any man in the world to uſe that in the leaſt would maintain his own right.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I beſeech you obſerve and judge, whether I have been ſo baſe, as to uſe any boiſterous courſes to get my own, other then what the law of <hi>England</hi> alowes to every man in the Nation; and if ſo, I hope I ſhall not be judged a mercileſs oppreſſor by you, for walking in the known Tracts and Footſteps of the Law of <hi>England.</hi> But moſt noble Senators, I perceive it is a ſtudied Artifice in this Age, for men that have more guilt upon Them then Their backs are able to bear, behinde perſons backs to ſtudy to reproach Thoſe They hate, and are pincht by, and to blaſt Their reputation; and therefore is it ſpoken privately up and down amongſt Parliament men, That I lately took a falſe Oath at <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi> Hall, about the Colliery at <hi>Harraton;</hi> unto which I ſhal an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer no more at preſent but This, That the buſineſs is of many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds conſequence <hi>per annum</hi> of concernment to other men, and I would be very loth in an haſty Apology for my ſelf, to let any thing drop that might give any juſt occaſion to the Judges There to be pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh, and thereby to have any colourable pretence to put off the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inall Judgement of the caſe longer then Tueſday next in the afternoon, the Time appointed for it after many days hearing, and many hours already expended in private debates amongſt the Judges Themſelves. And in the mean Time, I intreat every ingenious man to ſuſpend his cenſuring of me for a few days after the Judging of the ſaid cauſe; and if then I do not with as much eaſe blow off al that dirt that by art about that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is thrown upon me, as the wind blows the lighteſt of chaff be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, let me forfeit my reputation amongſt all ingenious men for ever; And Therefore at preſent to conclude, vouchſafe me liberty without diſtaſte to acquaint you, That at our grand day of hearing about that Colliery, Sir <hi>Arthur Heſilrig</hi> much inſiſted upon a Book I had lately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it writ againſt him; and therefore deſired the Commiſſioners freely to give me leave to lay all the evil in the world to his charge there; that I knew againſt him; unto which, when it came to my part to ſpeak, I told Them in theſe words or to this effect.</p>
            <p>That I very much commended Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> for his wiſdom to ſave himſelf, for he could not be ſo ignorant to immagine, but that I very well knew thoſe Commiſſioners had no power to queſtion him, for though it were, as he was there ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrator in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> (which mean and low Office I knew never a Parliament man in <hi>England,</hi> beſides himſelf, but he ſcorned to execute) he was under them, and ought to be obedient to their orders, &amp; to give them a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive an account of his actions; but as he was a Parliament man, and thereby one of the ſupreme Authority of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he was above them, and one of their Lords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120088:6"/>and if I were ſuch a child and fool to queſtion him for his offences before them that had no juriſdiction over him, (but abſolutely inferior to him) I ſhould be laught at for my pains, and they if they ſhould be ſo miſunderſtanding of their own Authority, as to aſſume juriſdiction over him upon my complaint, and thereupon go about to puniſh him, they might very well be clapt by the heels for their ſawſineſs, for breaking the priviledges of Parliament, in judging one of their Members, that they have no authority given them ſo to do unto.</p>
            <p>But as I told the Chair-man, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> ſaith, I have printed a book lately againſt him, in which he ſaith I call him Traytor, Tyrant, and worſe then <hi>Strafford:</hi> unto which I anſwered, to this effect, Sir, it is true, I have writ and cauſed a late book to be printed againſt him, in which its poſſible ſuch expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be, and if there are I will juſtifie and prove them at my utmoſt peril: and that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> and all the company may know that I am not afraid nor aſhamed to own the ſaid book; be it known to him, that ſince I laſt came to Town I took the boldneſs upon me, as to wait upon the General, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe command I look upon Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> (as he is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel) to be, and I told him a little of Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> Tyranny, which I told him was ſomwhat fully expreſſed in a late book of mine, one of which I gave him, and beged him to read it ſeriouſly, further telling him it was mine, and I would juſtifie it with my life, and earneſtly entreated him, that he would pleaſe to vouchſafe to take upon him the hearing and judging of the cauſe, and we would ty our ſelves in bonds to ſtand to his judgment, but he put it off as being full of buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Upon which in the ſecond place, hearing that in Parliament there was to be ſome queſtioning of the Speaker, I haſted away as faſt as I could to their Doore, ſuppoſing it a very fit ſeaſon for me to get my complaint againſt Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> heard before them, that have a proper juriſdiction over him; And at the Dore of the Parliament meeting with an honourable member of Parliament, called Mr <hi>Love,</hi> I told him what I heard the Houſe was to be about, and having in my hand (I was confident of it, a higher Charge againſt Sir <hi>Arthur Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlerig,</hi> then any could bee pretended againſt the Speaker) I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120088:7"/>therefore intreated him as he was a Gentleman, to take a Book of mee, in which it was contained; and acquaint the Houſe with it, and tell them, It was mine give to him to bring in, and I was at the Dore ready at their Bar to juſtifie and prove it. And (as I am informed) he did acquaint the Houſe with it, ſir <hi>Arthur</hi> himſelf being preſent, who it ſeems had not ſo much Innocency in his Breaſt, as to dare to preſſe to have me cald into juſtifie it: And therefore ſaid I to the Chairman, as earneſt as ſir <hi>Arthur</hi> is to deſire you to give me free liberty to lay all I can to his charge before you, that hee very well knows have no juriſdiction over him; ſo earneſt am I with him to queſtion me, and call me, if he dare, to the Bar of the Parliament (his proper Judges) to juſtifie my ſaid Book; and ſo much at preſent to Sir <hi>Arthur.</hi> And now, ſaid I, if you pleaſe Gentlemen, a word or 2 to ſom of you Commiſſioners. Som of you ſay, I have writ a Book, in which I have abuſed you. Its tru ſaid I, <hi>a Book I have written againſt you, but I have not belyed or abuſed you; &amp; if you pleaſe to joyn Iſſue with me, you ſhall find me very ingenuous, ready either as a Chriſtian, or an Engliſhman to give you full ſatisfaction.</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>As a Chriſtian, if you pleaſe to chooſe</hi> 2 <hi>honeſt godly men, I will chooſe</hi> 2 <hi>more, and bind my ſelf in large Bonds to ſtand to their Arbitration and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and if upon the hearing of both ſides, they ſhal find I have done you wrong, and judge it Juſt for me to repair you by a publique printed Recantation, I will freely do it with my Hand to it. Or,</hi> Secondly, <hi>If you like not this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, as a rationall Man, I will give you ſatisfaction, that is to ſay, if you pleaſe to enter your Action in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Bench, or any Court of Juſtice in England, I will appear to it</hi> gratis; <hi>and give you ſuch ſatisfaction as by the extremity of the law you can obtain, which I think is ſo fair, as no ingenious man in England can offer fairer.</hi> And therefore (Right Honorable) to conclude all, give me leave to make this Propoſition to you, ſeeing ſir <hi>Arthur</hi> indirectly ſtruggles ſo to maintain his guilt; That if you pleaſe to declare, That I may have as free liberty, and the ſame priviledges againſt ſir <hi>Arthur Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlerig,</hi> as your ſelves had againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> I do hereby engage my Life againſt his, in the behalf of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and bring into your Houſe, in a very ſhort time, as formal a charge in the ey of the Law, as high and criminal in its nature, againſt ſir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> as ever yours was againſt <hi>Strafford;</hi> and before you openly, by legal and good teſtimony to prove it, or otherwiſe let my life go for his.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So humbly craving pardon for my tediouſneſs, I take leave to ſubſcribe my ſelf, Your faithful Suppliant, who deſires to live no longer in this world, then he is able (the frailty of poor, weake feeble man ſet aſide) to juſtifie the honeſty of his Actions and Dealings with all private perſons whatever, before the Judgment ſeat of the ſtricteſt Juſticiarie in England.</hi> JOHN LILBURNE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>this 28 <hi>November,</hi> 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
